Guide to the Collection of Cabaret Theatre Club and Cave of the Golden Calf printed ephemera
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
Collection of Cabaret Theatre Club and Cave of the Golden Calf printed ephemera
1912-1914
MSS 50
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
.42
1 box, 11 items
The collection comprises 11 items of printed ephemera concerning the Cabaret Theatre Club and the Cave of the Golden Calf. The items include: a preliminary prospectus (April, 1912); a general program (May, 1912); a prospectus for the second season (September, 1912); a preliminary announcement of the performance season of the Intimate Theatre Society (late 1912?); a program for June 17, 1913, featuring a performance of Bastien und Bastienne; membership application forms for the Cabaret Theatre Club and the Intimate Theatre Society, along with a form for requesting the membership application form (1912 or 1913); and three printed envelopes, addressed to Robert Bevan, the last of which may be from the Rebel Art Centre.
Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England)
Crawley, Eric
Gore, Spencer Frederick, 1878-1914
Lewis, Wyndham, 1882-1957
Cave of the Golden Calf (London, England)
Intimate Theatre Society (London, England)
Biographical / Historical
The Cabaret Theatre Club, also frequently known as The Cave of the Golden Calf (a reference to its premises below street level at 9 Heddon Street, London) was a prominent nightclub created by Frida Strindberg, operating from 1912 to early 1914. It was associated with notable artists including Wyndham Lewis, Spencer Gore, Jacob Epstein, and Eric Gill, who contributed to its decor and emblems. Intended as a meeting place for writers, artists, and bohemians, the club may be considered the first British "gay bar" in the modern sense.
A general program for the club, May 1912 (f. 3), offers the "Aims and Programme" for the Club: "Our aims have the simplicity of a need: We want a place given up to gaiety, to a gaiety stimulating thought, rather than crushing it. We want a gaiety that does not have to count with midnight. We want surroundings, which after the reality of daily life, reveal the reality of the unreal. We want light and we want song. With these quite modest wishes we desire to harm nobody, unless it be such 'outre-mer' purveyors of entertainment as flourish, not necessarily on their merits so much as on the drastic dullness of our home-life ... Subjoined is, in an approximative and preliminary form, our first week's programme, the character of which can be best suggested by the names of some of the authors and composers under whose banners we range ourselves: Abercrombie, Villiers de l'Isle Adam, John Davidson, Walter Delamare, Arthur Machen, T. Sturge Moore, Ezra Pound, August Strindberg, Frank Wedekind, Yeats; Granville Bantock, Delius, Holbrooke, Raoul Lapara, Ernest Moret, Florence Schmitt, Dalhousie Young. ... Small tables--at which, up to 11, refreshments will be served, after 11, suppers--will be a welcome relief from the disciplinary ranks of theatre seats ..."
In his memoirs, Wyndham Lewis describes the venue: "This very adventurous woman [Strindberg] ... rented an enormous basement. Hence the term 'Cave'. She had it suitably decorated with murals by myself, and numbers of columns by Jacob Epstein: hired an orchestra -- with a frenzied Hungarian gypsy fiddler to lead it -- a smart corps of Austrian waiters and an Austrian cook; then with a considerable amount of press-promotion she opened as a night-club. With the Epstein figures appearing to hold up the threateningly low ceiling, the somewhat abstract hieroglyphics I had painted round the walls, the impassioned orchestra, it must have provided a kick or two for the young man about town of the moment ..." (Rude assignment: a narrative of my career up-to-date. London, New York: Hutchinson & Co., 1950).
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Yale Center for British Art, Friends of British Art Fund
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Related Materials
The collections of the Yale Center for British Art, Department of Prints and Drawings, also include 30 original drawings concerning the Cave of the Golden Calf. These include two drawings by Eric Gill for his bas-relief calf (B1985.25.9 and B1986.16.21) and 28 studies by Spencer Frederick Gore for the club's decorations.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises 11 items of printed ephemera concerning the Cabaret Theatre Club and the Cave of the Golden Calf. The items include: a preliminary prospectus (April, 1912); a general program (May, 1912); a prospectus for the second season (September, 1912); a preliminary announcement of the performance season of the Intimate Theatre Society (late 1912?); a program for June 17, 1913, featuring a performance of Bastien und Bastienne; membership application forms for the Cabaret Theatre Club and the Intimate Theatre Society, along with a form for requesting the membership application form (1912 or 1913); and three printed envelopes, addressed to Robert Bevan, the last of which may be from the Rebel Art Centre.
Bohemianism -- Great Britain; Futurism (Art) -- Great Britain; Modern dance -- Great Britain; Modernism (Art) -- Great Britain; Music-halls (Variety-theaters, cabarets, etc.) -- Great Britain; Nightclubs -- Great Britain; Restaurants -- Great Britain; Theater -- Great Britain; Vorticism; London (England) -- Social life and customs -- 20th Century; Application forms; Blank forms; Envelopes; Ephemera; Programs; Prospectuses; Bantock, Granville, Sir, 1868-1946; Bevan, Robert, 1865-1925; Crawley, Eric; Ginner, Charles Isaac, 1878-1952; Gore, Spencer Frederick, 1878-1914; Lewis, Wyndham, 1882-1957; Mansfield, Katherine, 1888-1923; Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791 ( Bastien und Bastienne); Rutherston, Albert, 1881-1953; Uhl, Frida, 1872-1943; Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); Cave of the Golden Calf (London, England); Camden Town Group; Intimate Theatre Society (London, England); Rebel Art Centre (London, England)
- Preliminary prospectus for the Cabaret Theatre Club, 1912 April; Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); Lewis, Wyndham, 1882-1957; Gore, Spencer Frederick, 1878-1914; 1 folded sheet ([2] pages); 26 x 32 cm, folded to 26 x 16 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Text of the prospectus:
  "Preliminary prospectus. The 'Cabaret Theatre Club' is now being permanently established.
  At 3, Heddon Street, Regent Street, London W., premises have been taken. The decoration will be entirely and exclusively the work of leading young British artists.
  ...
  From 9 o'clock to 11.30 a varied, programme, with the tendency of a return of art to intuition and simplicity, will be given. On one hand such art as we owe to the genius of the people, the dance, folk lore--on the other offering free development to the youngest and best of our contemporaries and--'Futurists.'
  The audience will sit around small tables. The cellars will be stocked by connoisseurs.
  From 11.30 Suppers--artistic suppers--(Brillat-Savarin was a great man). Spanish gipsies will play. Neapolitans sing. English poets say their verses, dancers dance ..."
  Includes terms of membership.
  Signed: "The Cabaret Theatre Club. April, 1912."
  Printed on parchment-like paper, by Verdier, Ltd.
  The top of the first page includes an illustration attributed to Wyndham Lewis or Spencer Gore. Water Michel notes: "Design from the preliminary prospectus. Inscribed 'Cave of the Calf' and "Cabaret-Theatre Club'. Possibly by Lewis but more florid and less incisive than his other Cabaret work. The design shows a frieze of calf and dancers ..." (Michel, no. 31).
  Cork notes: "This illustration, with its pronounced expressionist character, is probably the work of Wyndham Lewis ... But it may possibly have been designed in collaboration with Spencer Gore, whose style at this period could sometimes come remarkably close to Lewis's ..." ( Art beyond the gallery, page 69).
  Nightclubs; Music-halls (Variety-theaters, cabarets, etc.); Modernism (Art); Prospectuses; Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); Cave of the Golden Calf (London, England)
- Envelope from the Cabaret Theatre Club, addressed to Robert Bevan, 1912 April; Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); Lewis, Wyndham, 1882-1957; 1 envelope; 21 x 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
  The top third of the envelope bears an illustration, by Wyndham Lewis, showing dancers and a calf, above the words "Cabaret Theatre Club." The envelope may have been used to mail the club's Preliminary Prospectus (see f. 1).
  Described and reproduced in Cork's Art beyond the gallery, page 69. Not described in Michel.
  The envelope is addressed to "Robert Bevan Esq., 14 Adamson Road, Hampstead, N.W." It is postmarked "Ap. 19 [?] [19]12".
  Bevan was a founding member of the Camden Town Group.
  Envelopes (Stationery); Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); Cave of the Golden Calf (London, England); Bevan, Robert, 1865-1925
- General program for the Cabaret Theatre Club, Cave of the Golden Calf, 1912 May; Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); Lewis, Wyndham, 1882-1957; [12] pages; 28 x 22 cm. Pagination includes covers and plates. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Front cover: "Cabaret Theatre Club, The Cave of the Golden Calf. 9, Heddon Street, Regent Street, W." With an illustration by Wyndham Lewis (Michel no. 32.)
  Page [2]: blank.
  Page [3]: "A wall-decoration in the Cave of the Golden Calf. By Wyndham Lewis." (Michel, no. 33: "It is not known whether this design was actually made into a wall decoration.")
  Page [4]: blank.
  Page [5]: List of the committee, solicitors, and secretary.
  Page [6]: Description of the Cabaret Theatre Club, including details on management, premises, election of members, and privileges of membership. With Lewis's illustration of a three-headed figure (Michel no. 34).
  Page [7]: "Aims and programme of the Cabaret Theatre Club." Dated May, 1912.
  Page [8]: "Programme. Amongst others: Zette; Greville Moore; La Morenita; Margaret Morris and her Greek Children Dancers; Winifred Barnes; Eva Segunda; Nina; Nadio Sokoloff; Xantippe. Romany-Chals. Arthur Machen; Diogenes; Vernon D'Arnalle; the Three Imposters; Stacey Aumonier; Jean Rodor; Conti. Dalhousie Young. Some items: Veil Dance; Paul et Virginie; Jester Songs; Natural Selection; a Breton Wake; La Serva Padrona; Exultations; Cards; Magali; Diogenes' Tub; A Love Mask; Tarantella; Gipsy Folk-lore; Playing with Fire; Caprichos. The Midnight Mail."
  The border of the program is filled by a design by Lewis (Michel no. 36).
  Page [9]: "The Nautch girl. Composer: Graville Bantock. Designed by Albert Rothenstein. To be danced in the Cave of the Golden Calf, June 1912."
  Page [10]: blank
  Page [11]: Menu. The top margin is illustrated with a design by Lewis (Michel no. 37).
  Back cover: Wyndham Lewis's illustration of a dancer (Michel no. 38). Imprint at bottom: Miles & Co., Ltd. 68 & 70, Wardour Street, W.
  The program is also described in Art beyond the gallery, pages 80, 81, and 85: "... inside the brochure, a calf and leering worshippers rise up over the Cave's name and thrust themselves forward, half human and half animal, to signify the primitive savagery of the Cabaret. As if in response, two figures on another page fling themselves into a dithyrambic dance, arms scything and legs lunging ... but on the brochure's back page Lewis finally calls a halt to tall this frenetic activity with a stern figure who brandishes his commanding arm as imperiously as a warrior directing a battle."
  Nightclubs; Music-halls (Variety-theaters, cabarets, etc.); Modern dance; Programs; Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); Cave of the Golden Calf (London, England); Rutherston, Albert, 1881-1953; Bantock, Granville, Sir, 1868-1946
- Envelope bearing the "Cave of the Calf" three-headed figure, addressed to Robert Bevan, 1912 May 18; Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); Lewis, Wyndham, 1882-1957; 1 envelope; 26 x 31 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
  The three-headed figure, by Wyndham Lewis, is printed in the top left corner (see Michel no. 34).
  Addressed, in black ink: "Robert Bevan, Esqr., Adamson Road, Hampstead, N.W." With one penny stamp and postmark dated 18 May [19]12.
  The envelope may have been used to mail the club's general programme (see f. 3).
- Prospectus for the second season of the Cabaret Theatre Club, 1912 September; Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); Lewis, Wyndham, 1882-1957; Crawley, Eric; 1 folded sheet ([4] pages); 26 x 30 cm, folded to 26 x 15 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
  With three illustrations by Wyndham Lewis, on page [1] (Michel no. 32), page [2] (Michel no. 35), and page [4] (Michel no. 38). Imprint on page [4]: "Miles & Co., Ltd. ..."
  "The Cabaret Theatre Club re-opens for its second season on Tuesday, October 15th, next.
  The premises have now been completely adapted to the innovation of Restaurant and Theatre combined. The decorations are by Mr. Spencer Gore and Mr. Charles Ginner. Statue and Emblem of 'The Calf' by Mr. Eric Gill. Messrs. Norman Wilkinson and Albert Rothenstein have devised the stage.
  The Club now definitely takes its distinct place as a novelty in English life, as its Theatrical performance begins at 11:30 p.m. with practically no fixed closing hours ...
  Every night, Sundays included, Cabaret Performances will be given at 11.30 p.m. The best European Cabaret Artistes will be introduced to London in a rich change of programme. After 1.30, Gipsy Orchestra. International Minstrels. After 2 o'clock, dancing permitted ...
  A Super-Cabaret performance ... will take place once a week ..."
  Includes terms of membership and names of committee members. Signed: "Eric Crawley, Secretary. September, 1912."
  Nightclubs; Music-halls (Variety-theaters, cabarets, etc.); Prospectuses; Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); Cave of the Golden Calf (London, England)
- Preliminary announcement of the performance season of the Intimate Theatre Society, late 1912?; Intimate Theatre Society (London, England); Lewis, Wyndham, 1882-1957; 1 sheet ([1] page); 26 x 15 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
  The announcement is headed Wyndham Lewis's Cave of the Calf three-headed figure (Michel no. 34), above the words "Cabaret Theatre Club." The design is flanked by the words "Intimate" and "Theatre," printed vertically.
  "Preliminary announcement. The Intimate Theatre Society will, under temporarily the same artistic management as the 'Cabaret Theatre Club,' but forming an independent association, open a season of six months on January 15th, 1913, at the 'Cave of the Calf.'
  Performances will be given on two Sundays of each month, cultivating drama, opera, pantomime, vocal music and such delicate art of the past as adapts itself to the frame of an intimate stage, and more especially all such new art as in the strength of its sincerity allows simplicity.
  From among the following, twelve works will be produced during the first season: 'Deborah,' by Lascelles Abercrombie; 'Man's life,' by Leonid Andrejeff; 'Dream of an autumn evening,' by Gabriele d'Annunzio; 'Lysistrata,' by Aristophanes; 'The Brothers Karamasof,' by Dostojewski; 'Lady Juliet,' 'Playing with fire,' 'Comrades,' 'Swan white,' 'Death-dance,' by August Strindberg; 'The beggars' opera' (original version); 'Bastien et Bastienne,' by W.A. Mozart; 'Apothecary,' by Hayden; 'Orpheus,' by Monteverde; 'Maestro di Capella,' by Pergolese; 'Timon of Athens,' by Purcell; 'Le devin de village,' by Jean Jacques Rousseau.
  Special evenings, including vocal and instrumental music, will be devoted to composers. Florent Schmitt's 'Palais hanté' (after E.A. Poe) and "Salomé'; Arnold Schoenberg's 'Pierrot Lunaire' (after Albert Giraud), for the first time in England.
  Terms £2.2.0 a season. ...
  For further particulars apply to Eric Crawley, Secretary. 'Cave of the Calf,' 9, Heddon Street, Regent Street, London."
  There are no apparent records of performances given by the Intimate Theatre Society. See: Morgan, M. M. "Strindberg and the English Theatre." Modern Drama, vol. 7 no. 2, 1964, pp. 161-173.
  Music-halls (Variety-theaters, cabarets, etc.); Nightclubs; Theater -- Great Britain; Intimate Theatre Society (London, England); Cave of the Golden Calf (London, England); Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England)
- Program for June 17, 1913: Bastien und Bastienne, 1913 June; Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); Lewis, Wyndham, 1882-1957; 1 sheet ([1] page); 28 x 22 cm (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Text (top to bottom): "Tuesday, 17 June 1913, 8.30 p.m. Bastien und Bastienne. One act opera by Mozart--Parody by Katherine Mansfield. Princess Redfeather. Eve Balfour. Mona Limerick. Frank Harris. Cabaret. Gertrude Rolffs, Eric Hiller, Anton Dressler, Lilian Shelley. José de Moreas. Mona Limerick. 11.30 p.m. Anniversary supper."
  The border is filled with a design by Wyndham Lewis (Michel no. 36). The design and text were printed separately (the design in a dark green, the text in purple, probably typewritten).
  Programs; Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Bastien und Bastienne; Music-halls (Variety-theaters, cabarets, etc.); Nightclubs; Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); Cave of the Golden Calf (London, England); Mansfield, Katherine, 1888-1923
- Membership application form for the Cabaret Theatre Club, 1912 or 1913; Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); 1 sheet ([1] page); 27 x 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 8)
  The form briefly notes obligations of applicant members (regulations, dues). It includes blanks for the applicant's signature, name in full, address, description ("state other clubs"), date, proposed by, and seconded by. With administrative blanks at top for applicant no., register no., and dates received/elected.
  With note at bottom: "It is important that the candidate's profession (if any) should be stated. Married women should be described 'Wife of'"
  Application forms; Blank forms; Music-halls (Variety-theaters, cabarets, etc.); Nightclubs; Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); Cave of the Golden Calf (London, England)
- Membership application forms for the Cabaret Theatre Club and the Intimate Theatre Society, 1912 or 1913; Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); Intimate Theatre Society (London, England); 1 sheet; 26 x 15 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Comprises two forms (each 13 x 15 cm), joined by a perforated edge. The top form is for application to the Cabaret Theatre Club; the bottom form for application to the Intimate Theatre Society. The forms are identical, aside from the names of the Club/Society. For each, the address is 9, Heddon Street, Regent Street, W.
  Each form briefly notes the obligations of applicant members (regulations, dues). Includes blanks for signature, name in full, address, description ("state other clubs"), and date. With administrative blanks at top for applicant no., register no., and dates received/elected.
  Music-halls (Variety-theaters, cabarets, etc.); Nightclubs; Application forms; Blank forms; Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); Intimate Theatre Society (London, England); Cave of the Golden Calf (London, England)
- Request form for membership application form for the Cabaret Theatre Club, 1912 or 1913; Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); 1 sheet ([1] page); 13 x 20 cm. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Printed on a parchment-like paper.
  "To the Secretary, Cabaret Theatre Club, 3, Heddon Street, Regent Street, W. Please send me application form for membership of the Cabaret Theatre Club. Yours faithfully, Name [blank] Address [blank]"
  Nightclubs; Music-halls (Variety-theaters, cabarets, etc.); Application forms; Blank forms; Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); Cave of the Golden Calf (London, England)
- Envelope addressed to Mr. and Mrs. (Robert) Bevan, 1914?; Lewis, Wyndham, 1882-1957; 1 envelope; 10 x 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Addressed, in black ink: "Mr. & Mrs. Bevan, 14 Adamson Rd., N.W." With one penny stamp and postmark dated 28 Ap. [18]14.
  With a small printed design at top left, by Wyndham Lewis (Michel no. 126: "Reproduced in Blast no. 1, p. 125; Blast no. 2, p. 49; Ezra Pound, 'Wyndham Lewis' in The Egoist, June 1914; also on the prospectuses for the Rebel Art Centre and the Rebel Art Centre Art School, and as an emblem on Rebel Art Centre envelopes.")
  Envelopes (Stationery); Cabaret Theatre Club (London, England); Cave of the Golden Calf (London, England); Rebel Art Centre (London, England); Bevan, Robert, 1865-1925